

# Nuno Miguel MARTINS PACHECO

LinkedIn: martinspacheco

Homepage: www.nmmp.de

E-mail: nmmp@outlook.de

# **PROFILE**

I am a creative and determined project manager with over 6 years of experience in product development. Specialising in design thinking and agile methods, I have proven that I can translate customer needs into successful product strategies. I have a background in mechanical engineering and am currently completing my PhD in product development at TUM. During my time at university, I have worked in leading positions with industrial partners such as BMW, MAN and Siemens as well as academic partners such as Imperial College London. My passion is to have a positive impact on organisations and people through innovative projects and effective team leadership. I enjoy working in teams, taking responsibility and delivering projects that create real value for customers and organisations.

# WORK EXPERIENCE

07/2019 - Current

#### RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

10/2021 - Current

#### MCube STEAM in collaboration with BMW, MAN, SWM and Stanglmeier

- Co-Project Lead: Responsible for project progress monitoring, implemented regular progress reports and workshops that improved communication and collaboration with project partners
- Leading the concept development: Integrated bus system for passenger and parcel transport in public transport, which increased bus utilisation by ~20% and saved ~180 kg CO2 per bus line each day
- Leading the realisation of the VR demonstrator: Presented at the IAA Mobility 2023, which was tested by over 120 exhibition visitors and received ~90% positive feedback (technology acceptance survey)

07/2019 - Current

#### THINK. MAKE. START. in collaboration with BMW

- Co-organiser: Successful implementation of 6x one-week sprints to develop customer-centric, innovative products, with some projects receiving €50k budget through management support for further development as part of pre-development
- Coaching cross-functional teams: Teaching skills in prototyping, storytelling and design thinking, which improved employees' skills in cross-functional collaboration, customer understanding and innovative thinking

07/2019 - 03/2024

# THINK. MAKE. START. in collaboration with UnternehmerTUM, Makerspace and Zeidler Research Association

- Project Lead: Successful organisation and implementation of 8x two-week sprints as a university seminar, which led to the creation of an average of one startup per sprint (e.g., Angsa Robotics) and received an average course rating of 1.1 from students (~400 students)
- Coaching interdisciplinary teams: Teaching skills in prototyping, storytelling, design thinking, and product strategy, enabling students to develop user-centred, economically viable products and enhance their innovative thinking abilities

02/2022 - Current

## **FREELANCER**

Mintech Engineering GmbH, Garching, Germany

- Concept Developer & Workshop Instructor: Development and successful realisation of 4 newly designed, technology-focused design thinking and prototyping workshops for customers (e.g. BMW, Siemens), whose success was confirmed by positive customer feedback and follow-up projects
- Coaching cross-functional teams: Teaching skills in brainstorming, prototyping, storytelling, and design thinking, which significantly improved the problem-solving and innovation abilities of the participants

#### **EDUCATION**

09/2019 - Current

#### PhD. DOCTOR'S DEGREE, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Specialisation: Product development of mechatronics products, design sprints
- PhD Thesis: A Hackathon Approach for Design Education to Enable Quantitative Analysis of Effort Spent, Product Concept Quality, and Learning Effect in Technical Higher Education (Thesis submitted 05/2024)

12/2022 & 05/2023

#### VISITING RESEARCHER, DESIGN ENGINEERING

Imperial College London, London, England

10/2016 - 05/2019

#### M.Sc. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND MANAGEMENT

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Specialisation: Product development, production and innovation
- Master Thesis: Prototyping Recommendation Framework; A Collection of Prototyping Methods for Early-Stage Product Development (Technical University of Denmark, 05/2019)

02/2018 - 06/2018

#### SEMESTER ABROAD, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Instituto Superior Técnico (IST), Lisbon, Portugal

10/2011 - 10/2011

# **B.Sc. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND ECONOMICS**

Technical University of Graz (TUG), Graz, Austria

- Specialisation: Engineering sciences with a foundation in natural sciences and business economics
- Bachelor Thesis: Business Creation, Factors Influencing this Decision, and Importance of Entrepreneurial Universities

02/2002 - 06/2011

# **GENERAL HIGHER EDUCATION QUALIFICATION**

Taunusgymnasium Königstein, Königstein im Taunus, Germany

# KNOWLEDGE AND SKILLS

# Language Skills

German (native), English (business fluent), Portuguese (native), Spanish (basic), Italian (basic)

# IT Skills

MS Office (very good), Miro (very good), Adobe Creative Cloud (good), Notion (good), Trello (good), Confluence (very good), Jira (basic), Python (basic), R (good), Figma/Adobe XD (basic)

# **Special Skills**

Design Thinking, project management, communication skills, problem solving skills, cross-functional collaboration, stakeholder management

## OTHER

# Memberships

Design Society (since 2019), Verein Deutscher Ingenieure (since 2023), Deutscher Alpenverein (since 2024)

## **Interests**

Road Biking (e.g., Munich to Bozen), Hiking (Alps, Norway, Portugal), Vinyl (Rock, Ambient, Electronic), Analog Photography (Urban & Nature), Cooking (Italian, Portuguese), Hackathon Participation (Best concept Vitra Work 2019, Best Prototype TMS #6 2017)